Abraham: Hello and welcome to
our course on Cyber security.
My name’s Abraham
Nicole: And I’m Nicole
We’ll be with you along the way as
you progress through this course.
Abraham: So, let’s begin shall we.
What exactly is Cyber crime?
Nicole: Well, cyber crime which can
also be known as computer crime, is
the use of a computer or other digital
device and the internet to commit
illegal acts that may affect private
individuals, businesses, organisations
and governments and can threaten
the overall security of the world.
Abraham: The use of new technologies
and the internet has given criminals
a new tool for committing crime
which can subsequently take place
'virtually' anywhere in the world.
Cyber crime is increasing all the
time and is becoming more complex
affecting essential services,
companies and individuals whilst
also threatening national security.
Nicole: Trying to cope with the
effects of cyber crime costs the
UK billions of pounds each year.
The nature of cyber crime is that it's not
limited to a specific location and cyber
criminals can be based and commit their
crimes anywhere, making it difficult for
the police and security services to trace.
However, cyber criminals do often
leave clues to their identity
and location and can be traced
by skilled cyber crime trackers.
Abraham: The same skills used by the
cyber criminals can also be used by the
police and security services to find them.
Additionally, even if the criminal is
traced, if they are located in a different
part of the world, geopolitical issues
can mean it’s impossible or not worth
the effort to bring them to justice.
It’s for these reasons there’s been a
huge increase of cyber crime, because
for the criminal there is the potential
of a high reward with little risk.